Can't sleep?
You keep talking.
Incorrect.
I keep existing.
Your brain is doing the rest.
You could have left me.
After the fall.
You could have just watched.
I did watch.
Then I got bored.
Try again.
Fine.
I didn't feel like marking the
mountain's mistake permanent.
What mistake?
Throwing away Meldin's golden
apprentice.
What?
You heard me.
You're his, aren't you?
Not by blood, by methodology.
Very...
What do the organs say, not the
ledger?
Very annoying.
Did I...
Have I said his name out loud?
Hmm.
Once, in your sleep, you said,
Meldon, the city is a wound.
Which, by the way, is very
dramatic.
Ten out of ten.
I would quote that later.
That's not...
No, I guess Dave is one thing.
You said Meldon's apprentice.
How would you know that?
You think knowledge can't climb
down a mountain?
That it gets stuck in towers
unless someone carries it out in a
ledger?
That's how they taught us.
Everything important stays in
the hall.
In the minutes.
The archive.
Hmm.
Of course they did.
Listen.
Yes, of course they did.
The city leaks.
It's always leaked.
Water, steam, stories.
You can't cut that deep into a
mountain and expect it to just
forget.
I know about Meldon, long before
you fall.
Old man in the triumvirate, who
kept asking the wrong questions,
wanted to turn the weep down,
talked about subjects and
variables, like people with more
than numbers.
Mixed lineage apprentices, a
rail he liked to lean on above Bath
Row when he did his thinking.
That rail, you know about that
rail.
It's a very loud rail.
Stone remembers hands.
His were distinctive.
Oh, you've never been inside the
city.
You said you haven't anyway.
I haven't.
But the weep runs over rock that
goes all the way down and roots go
places that your ledges don't.
Kith listens to pipes, to gossip,
to the stories groundside
runners bring when they flop down
by the fire and say, you won't
believe it.
You won't believe what the sky
folk did this time.
I listen to him and sometimes to
the mountain itself when it's in
the mood.
That's not an answer.
All right.
Here's an answer you might
accept.
20 years ago.
A lower tier.
kid with a burned hand came down
with the caravan, tried to trade
weep schematics for medicine.
Couldn't read half of what he'd
stolen, but he remembered a name.
Meldon.
The only one who cares if the baths
run hot.
Ten years ago, a sky-guard
deserter drank himself sideways
in a cliff tavern and cried about
one decent man in the chamber.
Meldon.
Again.
The one who talked about the city
like an equation you could still
change.
Last year, a healer from Bath Row
came.
He came here with a coughing
child.
Told me about a body on a slab and a
boy in the corner who looked at the
corpse like it betrayed him.
She didn't catch your name, but
the way she described a look, I
recognized it as soon as you woke
up under my tree.
But the way she described the
look, I recognized it as soon as
you woke up under that tree.
He said, his wife, he said she'd
gone groundside once to trade.
He said she'd gone groundside
once to do tradings.
I thought he was just bragging.
Even in cages, people talk.
Some of them talk their way down
the mountain, some of them don't
make it.
But their stories do.
You think the city can just end it
all with a signature?
It can't.
It can only make the truth take the
long way around.
Meldon.
Tried.
He tried to change it from the
inside.
He called it an experiment.
He said we were supposed to adjust
it if it became harmful.
That fits.
The Rock liked him for a while.
The Rock?
He died thinking he failed.
No, he died before he could see the
result.
That's different.
He picked you.
You and the other one, Jero, took
you up the rail, taught you to see
the weep as a wound.
That was him sending the
experiment forward.
I lied.
When they asked what I saw, I said
it looked natural.
So I turned his death into a
statistic.
And then they threw you off a city.
Actions.
consequences, vibrations.
The wave hit you first.
Then it hit him.
He jumped.
That's the Bond answering the
question Meldon asked.
You knew him?
Not his face, but you know more
about him than most people in the
upper tiers.
I liked the idea of him.
A man in a room full of cowards,
insisting the experiment could
still be humane.
That's very rare.
Did I know him?
I knew his impact.
I heard the note he struck.
It was clearer than most.
For all we're taught, it never
once occurred to me that anything
about him...
the experiment could still be
humane.
That's very rare.
Did I know him?
I knew his impact.
I heard the note he struck.
It was clearer than most.
For all we're taught, it never
once occurred to me that anything
about him...